Thanks for watching AM Northwest. If you love to
shop for art at garage sales or antique shops,
how do you know if that piece of art is worth
something? Here to share his expert tips,
we welcome back antique appraiser Gary
Germer. Good to see you. How are you doing?
I'm swell. Doing great.
Good. This is the number
one question you get.
This is the number one question I get. We're at
our appraisal clinics and when we do appraisal
people ask me, the grandma had this work
of art. Is it worth anything? What is it?
What am I
looking at? And I put this together and I had
a two hour lecture that I had to pare down to
six
minutes. So we got to, we'll end up
flying through this. Okay, let's do it.
What you're looking at, and here's the
first thing you're going to need is a tool.
Let me give you
this one. You can give you the cheap one. This
is actually a linen press thing. You don't,
you need a three, a 30 power loop so you can get
down to see the surface of what you're looking
at.
Okay, gotcha. And we're talking about
flat art and that comes into two,
basically two groups.
You have original art, which is a painting
where somebody's actually painted it. And you
prints, which is a big umbrella term that
people misunderstand. They fall into two basic
groups. You've got the artist made prints
and there's a thousand ways of doing it.
There can be,
you know, but it involves some sort of a
block or where they make a multiple like a,
like in a
printing press. Sure. And then, or it
could be wood block. There's many systems,
but they're an
artist made work of art and they can be valuable.
And then you have the photo mechanically reproduced
and that's what we see the most of. And that's
when you see when you're most likely not going
to have that antique roadshow moment
that you've now made a million dollars.
So what we want to do
is want to take one here. We're going to look
at this and you want to take your loop and you
want
to kind of look to see what the surface is.
Now yours, you just set that on there flat.
You set it,
let go of it, let go of it. Just look right
down. Oh, and what you're going to see is this,
you're
going to put this little graphic for the
people because it's really riveting television.
You and
I looking at them. Yeah. And you're
looking for the three color dot separation.
I just saw the dot.
And it's a bunch of dots. If you end up with
something like this and if it's a black and white
photo, sometimes you'll end up with black
and white dots. If you have the dots,
you've got a photo
mechanically and you've got an inexpensive
print poster, something like that.
Purely decorative
value. Rarely is it worth very much other than
decorative value. Okay. We then look at these
type of prints here and these is just a selection.
They can be also woodblock prints as a woodblock
print. This is a, uh, this is
a mezzotint that's an etching.
One of the things you're looking at here in a
modern print that you can tell it's not a real
pen and ink drawing is look how it's impressed
right there. You can almost feel it where the
plate has pushed into the paper. And on this
one, you can see and then it's signed in pencil
on the edges. An artist will paint in the painting,
but on the edge, that means the artist himself
made the print.
I see. Usually it has a number of how
many, so 96 prints out of a hundred.
Exactly. And that lets you know after
the hundred, they destroyed the print.
They stopped.
And they stopped making it.
And so it comes in black and white. There's
also, this is a Japanese woodblock print and they
can vary in value. You have this
Japanese one here. It's worth about $400.
You got this one here. It's a Seattle
artist. My, one of my favorite pieces I have,
and it's worth maybe 50 bucks. This is made by
Rembrandt. This print here and that the plate
itself was made by Rembrandt.
Wow.
The plate has lasted all these years.
Yeah.
This was printed in the mid 20th century.
Wow.
So it's worth instead of if it
had been one he himself did.
It's in the tens of thousands of dollars.
Right.
This is worth about $2,000.
$2,000. So let me ask you this though,
because I'm a big believer. If you love art,
you love what you love. And if it
speaks to you, it speaks to you.
Right.
It's the only reason to buy art, period.
Yeah. It's only if it
means something to you.
Right.
So even the print can
mean something to you too.
Absolutely. And yeah, absolutely.
And you'll find, and usually they do.
And just because it's not valuable
doesn't mean you don't love it.
Right. Exactly.
But this is how you might find a treasure.
So if you have something
that's a print like this,
it's an artist-made print
you find at a garage sale,
it's worth investigating.
Is it a $50 one or is it a $2,000 one?
Sure, okay.
And then we get down to
original paintings here.
And one of the things you're looking at,
again, I'm going to steal this one here
because it's out of the frame,
loop if you're looking at brushstrokes okay
and you're gonna see in a painting you're gonna
see
brushstrokes if you see and the other thing to
look at the brushstrokes and this sounds really
crazy but what you want to look is make sure that
the color is following the brushstroke because
they make prints and she clays on textured
canvases and textured boards and then they make
a print on it so holding it up looking from afar
it looks like a painting you see all the groups
but it's not as you clay is a very is an it's a
relatively new animal isn't it it's a less yeah
and they look like real paintings they really do
until you get your loop out and you start seeing
little dots right but what you're looking at
is making sure there's no dots and then does it
have
brushstrokes if it's completely flat it's quite
probably a print like there's a color print
okay
those are the main things
that you're going to be
looking at when you're making a painting and
it's not just a painting it's a painting of a
painting that you're looking for and each one
of these could get broken down you know further
and
study each type of print in each one but mainly
remember if you if they're walking away with
one
thing and this seems really remedial but if
you but it it I get this all the time have your
loop
and you're looking for the dots yeah looking
for the dots and you're looking for the dots if
you
have the dots that's going to eliminate half of
the artwork people find at garage hills or more
so if
you're out there just have it look at it and go
oh God it looks great yeah what about the idea
that
there's
a painting under a painting paintings under
well that you mean where they that's way out of
our
league right yeah that's yeah that's sort of
like wouldn't knowing the winning lottery ticket
numbers
because I mean there have been painters who
painted over another painting they didn't like
and though they have underneath what I see
actually more often that we'll find at estate sales
and
garage sales is you'll find something and they
buy it because they like the frame it has an
ugly
picture in it and they take it apart and there's
a painting behind it that's worth right and
people
would or print or something behind it right
right right right right right right right right
right
and I get that a lot people is this anything
and I go yeah this is you know yeah you're right
so people
buy it just for the frame the frames are very
expensive right absolutely so like you said if
you're going to be going out and you're a
weekend lawyer out at the estate sales take along
your
take along your loop that's actually made for
uh counting threads and Linen is what that was
originally made for but I'm a person that has
to do that you can make sure you're getting the
your value on your right my 800 count right I
got it but that's great because you just set it
down
and you don't set it and forget it.
Gary, great information.
Thank you very much.
We'll put all of that on
our website at kt.org.